so basically what i have here is a
system that saves each part of the map
as
a scene and loads it as a chunk
surrounding the player for this example
i'm just
using squares that display a random
color so this video is mainly just going
to be an overview video
i'll just be explaining how the code
works
so the first thing that i want to show
you is the world saved script
which as you can see is a singleton this
singleton stores the data for each chunk
in the map
in two linked arrays basically what i
mean by two linked arrays is just that
the elements that are added into the
arrays are added at the same time
therefore they share the exact same
index so as you can see in the add
function
the chunks coordinates is passed in and
stored in the loaded coordinates array
and an empty array is added into the
chunk data array
basically what that does is that it adds
an empty array for a chunk with that
specific
chunk coordinates that basically means
that the trunk coordinates can serve as
a key which is going to access
the data in the chunk data array with
the exact same index
as you can see in this save and retrieve
functions the coordinates are used to
access the data in the chunk data array
and now for the node itself that will
contain each part of the map
in this scene we just have a color rect
and a label
the colorectal is used to display the
color and the label is used to display
the
chunk coordinates inside the chunk node
script it has a function called starts
which passes in its trunk coordinates
then it checks if that coordinates has
already been loaded before
and if it has then it retrieves the data
for that exact coordinates
and if it hasn't then to add that
coordinates and then generate a new
color and that
color is then saved into an array and
finally we have the save function
this function basically saves data into
the world save singleton
and then deletes the chunk from the
scene tree
lastly in our main world we have the
player character on the camera and
inside the world script which is the
script that handles the chunk loading we
have a chunk node preload
and a reference to the player on some
variables
first we have the render distance then
the chunk size then the current chunk
which stores the chunk coordinates of
the player and the previous chunk which
starts to play as previous chunk
coordinates
and now we have two arrays one that
stores the coordinates of the chunks
that have been loaded
and the other that stores the chunk
nodes that have been loaded so on the
ready function we just make a reference
to the player
then we get the current chunk by using
the get chunk coordinates function
and then we pass in our play as global
position this function returns the
player's position in trunk coordinates
so then in our process function we check
if the previous chunk is not equal to
the current chunk which basically means
that the player has moved from one chunk
to another
and in that case we then call the load
chunk function
so in our load chunk function the first
thing we want to do is get our render
bounds
our render bounds is basically the size
of our two-dimensional array which is
determined by a render distance using
this formula
basically what that means is that when
our render distance is one we want to
make a
three by three grid and when our render
distance is two we'd want to make a five
by five grid
and so on then we'll calculate the
coordinates of each chunk using this
formula and then offset it by the
player's current strong coordinates
and after that we'll add it to the
loading chunk array which stores the
coordinates for the chunks that are
supposed to be surrounding the player
then we'll check if the coordinates of
the chunk that is about to be loaded has
already been loaded
and if it hasn't then we'll load the
chunk
lastly we check every coordinates in the
coordinates that have been loaded
that is not part of the coordinates that
should be loaded
then we add into the deleting chunk
array and for each coordinates in the
deleting chunk array we call it
chunk node's save function then we
remove its coordinates and its chunk
node from the respective arrays
and that concludes the code for chunk
loading
i also wrote this project in c-sharp and
the links are in the description so if
you want to
play around with the code or add it to
your own project you can do that